查理
Charlie!
我担心你赶不上这班巴士
I wasn't so sure you'd be on the bus.
不想让你的白人弟兄们误以为
Didn't want your white brothers thinking
你是我们族里最优秀的人才
you were the best we had.
所罗门群岛 1943年
小心
Watch out!
我的手
My hand!
他妈的
Goddamn!
快没子弹了，我们得快走
We're running out of ammo. We gotta get out of here.
前进
Move!
过来
Come on!
过来，你办得到的
Come on, you can do it! Come on!
完全没弹药了，恩得斯， 我们没弹药了
We got nothin', Enders! We're out of ammo!
乔伊，我们不该再平白牺牲，现在撤退还来得及
Joe... Nobody else needs to die. We can go! We can get outta here!
我们身负任务
We got orders!
上面要我们守住这个点，我们就得死守在这里
They told us to hold the position! And that's what we're gonna do!
起来，阿兵哥，死守下去
Get up, marine! Hold the goddamn position!
拼啦
Come on!
趴下
Get down!
汤米
Tommy.
该死的家伙
Goddamn you!
不
Oh, no! No!
- 比尔 - 我没子弹了
- Bill! - I'm out.
过来
Come on! Come on!
你他妈的，乔伊・恩得斯
Goddamn you, Joe Enders.
不
No... No!
No!
右手举起来
Raise your right hand.
- 我…说自己的名字… - 我，班亚吉…
- I... State your full name... - I, Ben Yahzee...
彭德尔顿营 加利福尼亚
兹誓言支持并保护美国宪法
..do solemnly swear to support and defend the constitution of the US...
抵御任何敌人，不论国内或国外…
..against all enemies, foreign and domestic... ..against all enemies, foreign and domestic...
日本人称之为“箱子”，谁知道“坦克”的密码？
Jap Ha-Go. Who can give me the code word for "tank"?
你们想成为密码战士
Come on. You boys wanna be codetalkers.
那就要有脑袋啊，快想
Show me some brains. Think!
我们怎么说坦克？
What do we call a tank?
Chay-da-gahi.
乌龟，很好
Tortoise. Good.
大炮，密码？
Artillery. Code word?
请说密码，白马二等兵
In code. Private Whitehorse.
Be-al-doh-tso-lani?
很好
Very good.
日本零式战机，密码？
Japanese Zero. Code word?
肯尼欧湾美国海军医院 1943
现在撤退还来得及
We can go! We can get outta here!
上面要我们守住这个点
They told us to hold the position!
天气真好啊
Nice day, huh?
乔伊？
Joe?
Joe.
你根本没听到我在说话，对吧？
Didn't hear a word, did you?
男人碰到美女不都是这样
That's what happens to a man when he's talking to a beautiful woman.
你不读我的唇语才会这样
It happens when you're not watching my lips, Joe.
你看我
Watch this.
你还没康复，骗不了人的
You're a mess, Joe. You're not fooling anybody.
不，丽塔，他才是还没康复
No, Rita. He's a mess.
我每天都在康复中
I'm getting better every day.
你中耳破损，平衡感不正常
You got a perforated eardrum, Enders. Your equilibrium's all screwy.
站都站不起来怎么重回战场
You can't go back to war if you can't stand up.
走吧，胜利不会从天上掉下来
Let's go, marines. This war ain't gonna wait forever. Let's go.
乔伊？
Joe...
为什么你不好好留下来？
Why don't you just stay here, Joe?
总得有人留下来陪妇女救护团
Somebody's gotta keep the WAVES company.
你到底帮不帮我？
Are you gonna help me or not?
丧失听力
改善很多了
Marked improvement.
他左耳情况比较差吗？
And his left ear is the worse of the two?
好得真快
It's... amazing.
TBY型的范围比不上TBX
TBY hasn't got the range of the TBX.
所以讯号可能要分程传递
So you may need a relay to get your transmission to command post.
但重点是压力下的速度与精准
But what it really comes down to is speed and accuracy under pressure.
开始解读
Transcribe now.
维多，这是X光，完毕
Victor, Victor. This is X-ray. Over.
可恶，我方弟兄遭炮火攻击
Damn it! We got a unit under fire!
伤亡惨重
We're losing men.
请解读这段讯息
I need this message decrypted.
“请求炮火支援，目标在119，B15”
"Request fire support. We have target at one-one-niner, Baker one-five."
“碉堡有重机枪，请立刻开火”
"Pillbox with heavy machine gun. Fire at will."
初学者手气好
Beginner's luck.
换你了，大哥
You're up, mac.
- 恩得斯下士报到，长官 - 稍息
- Corporal Enders reporting, sir. - At ease.
你的表现相当不错，下士
You've done well as a marine, Corporal.
比从军前的行为好多了
Better than you did as a civilian.
偷窃撞毁机车，遭高中勒令退学
Stole a motorbike, crashed it. Got kicked out of high school.
袭击并殴打克里宾欧唐诺神父
Assault and battery... on one Father Crispin O'Donnell?
连教士都打？
A priest?
他是齐纳主教高中副校长兼训导主任
Assistant principal at Archbishop Keenan High School, sir, and head disciplinarian.
我以前念的是公立学校
Public-school boy myself.
训练中心时还是小错不断
Some minor problems in boot.
在上海获颁最佳勇气奖
A commendation for valor in Shanghai.
死守所罗门群岛表现杰出
And you made a hell of a stand on the Solomons.
那儿很苦吧？
Tough bit of business there, huh?
相当艰苦，长官
Pretty tough, sir.
可是，你想再回去？
But you're prepared to jump right back into it?
是的，长官，非常想
Yes, sir. Very much so.
非常想
Very much so.
可是…
Well...
我们的密码全遭日军破解
The Japs have pretty much busted every code we've thrown at 'em, Corporal.
你在所罗门群岛的弟兄，因密码被破解全部阵亡
You men on the Solomons were lost to a broken code.
在所罗门碰到过印地安人吗?
Tell me something. You ever run into any Indians on the Solomons?
- 印地安人，长官？ - 正确的说，应该是纳瓦荷人
- Indians, sir? - Navajo, to be exact.
军方用他们的语言，发展出一套新密码
The Corps has developed a new code based on their language.
评价相当不错
It's had quite an impact.
所以海军总部下令全力保护它
So much so the navy have decided to go to great lengths to protect it.
这就是找你来的原因
That's why you're here.
你将与密码战士配对，全力保护他们
You're to pair with one of them, keep his ass safe.
你负责保护他们的性命，以利他们执行密码任务
Your job is to keep him alive so he can do his job.
抱歉，我的专长是屠杀日军
Begging the major's pardon, but I believe I'd best serve the Corps killing Japs,
不是照顾印地安人
not baby-sitting some Indian.
我们不是随便挑到你的
Enders, we didn't pick your name out of a hat.
我们需要的是杰出陆战队员
We need good marines.
所以才选上你
That's why you're standing here.
你看
Take a look.
他就是个纳瓦荷人…应该死了
It's a Navajo. Or it was.
遭日军逼问密码，严刑拷打致死
Tortured to death by Japanese intelligence trying to bust our code.
所幸，他想说也说不出所以然
Fortunately, he couldn't help them even if he wanted to.
- 长官？ - 他是纳瓦荷人但不是密码战士
- Sir? - Man's a Navajo, not a codetalker.
密码由他们的语言编成，但毕竟还是密码
Code's based on their language, but it is still a code.
东条巴不得活捉一个密码战士
Tojo would like nothing more than to catch a live one.
我以下的话，绝不能泄漏出去
What I'm about to tell you, Corporal, cannot leave this room.
不管在任何情况下，密码战士绝不能落入敌人手中
Under no circumstances can you allow your codetalker to fall into enemy hands.
你的任务是保护密码
Your mission is to protect the code...
不惜任何代价
at all costs.
懂我的意思吗？
You understand me?
是的，长官，我懂
Yes, sir, I do.
很好
Good.
恭喜你，你刚获升中士
Congratulations. You just made sergeant.
手臂保持垂直
Keep those hands vertical.
不错，阿兵哥
Way to go, marine.
佛第诺，接替我一下
Fortino, take over.
少校办公室外的是你，对吧？
Hey... That was you, right, sitting in front of the major's office?
我叫彼得韩德森
Yeah. Listen, I'm Pete Henderson.
他们叫我公牛 不是因为我的肌肉
They call me Ox. Not cos of my big muscles or anything.
是因为我住在加州公牛城 好莱坞北边一点点
I'm from Oxnard, California. Just north of Hollywood a ways.
你也是两栖作战通讯连的人?
So you're with JASCO too, huh?
请问两栖通讯二分队怎么走?
Hey, know where we might find 2nd Joint Assault Signal?
没听说过,老土
No fuckin' idea, mac.
多谢
Thanks. Thanks a bunch.
从没看过那么多白人
I've never seen so many white men.
他们也没看过那么多纳瓦荷人
They've never seen so many Navajo.
看起来你上过战场
Looks to me like you got to see a little action there.
我也是
Me too.
屁股挨了日本鬼子的子弹
Jap sons of bitches shot me right in the ass.
相不相信? 并不是我想逃避上前线
You believe that shit? I wasn't running or nothin'.
你在两栖通讯的任务 跟这些纳瓦荷通信兵有关吗?
So, your duty with JASCO have anything to do with these Navajo radiomen?
我奉命守密
I'm not at liberty to say.
我发现你升官了,我也是
I see you got a new stripe there. Me too.
我猜,你不能说的秘密 跟我不能说的是一样
So I'm guessing the orders you can't tell me are the same orders I can't tell you.
了不起的任务吧?
Hell of a thing, huh?
身不由己,中士,这里是军队
Ain't a democracy, Sergeant. It's the marines.
他们看起来蛮正常的
They look pretty normal, I guess.
难道他们得喷上迷彩?
Expecting them to wear war paint?
或许该过去打个招呼 他们好像迷路了
Maybe we ought to go introduce ourselves. They look a little lost to me.
韩德森
Henderson.
我不想跟他们太亲近
I wouldn't get too friendly.
怎么样?
How!
开个玩笑,我叫公牛
Just kiddin'. I'm Ox.
我叫白马
Whitehorse.
他姓亚吉,叫班
This is Yahzee. Ben.
-下一位 -漂亮
- Next. - Beautiful. Beautiful.
闭着眼睛会比较好吃 下一个是谁?
Close your eyes. It'll taste better. Who's next?
可以一起吃吗?
Mind if I join you?
我叫班亚吉,跟你同一组
I'm Ben Yahzee. Guess the Corps paired us up.
你好吗?
How you doin'?
你挡住我的视线了
You're blocking my view.
对不起
Oh, sorry.
这难吃的东西是什么?
What do they call this crap anyway?
军方称之为食物
Marines call it chow.
有广告不实的嫌疑哦
Well, there's a propaganda effort.
对不起,我的赔你
Sorry. You can have mine.
啊,糟糕
Shit.
你说你叫什么名字,二兵?
What'd you say your name was again, Private?
我叫班亚吉
It's Yahzee. Ben Yahzee.
端着
Hold this.
可恶
Shit.
你的白人搭档怎么样？
How's your white man?
饥饿
Hungry.
我再玩几把
I'm in for a couple more.
写信给你儿子？
You writing to your son?
帮我问个好
Tell him I say hello.
大恩先生K一对
Pair of cowboys for Big E.
-希腊人可能是顺子 -可能是一手乌龙啦
- Possible straight for the Greek. - Possible thumb up the Greek's ass.
小伙子2一对,有前途
Oh, a pair of twos for the kid. Lookin' good.
有人胆子不小
- Oh, come on! - Now there's a bold move.
好啦
All right.
佛州小子陷入两难
OK... Oh, another mess for the Sunshine State.
-你对我不爽? -我只是想赢你的钱
- What, are you mad at me? - Just want your money.
9三条!漂亮
Hey! Look at that. A trio of nines. Pretty.
-你牌到底有没有洗? -当然有
- You shuffle that deck? - I certainly did.
9喊,我加两毛五
Nines bets. I'll raise it two bits.
我跟
Call.
我们都是一手烂牌
We all got thumbs up our asses.
玩不久了,我朋友在军机处 他说我们下周开拔
You won't for much longer. I got a buddy in Intel that says we ship out in a week.
“下周”已经说一个月了
I been hearing "next week" for a month.
我不知道你有朋友在军机处
I didn't know you knew anybody in Intelligence, Harri.
拖到明年我也无所谓
Next year'd be all right with me.
各位,哭吧,9带4
Gentlemen, read 'em and weep. Look at that. Nines and fours.
葫芦
Full boat, baby.
K带Q葫芦,哭死你
Cowboys over queens. Read 'em and die.
这怎么可能!
Oh, Jesus!
-我不玩了 -我要去写信给老婆
- Fuck it. I'm out. - Yeah. I'm gonna go write the missus.
天知道女人收不到音讯会干嘛
God knows what a girlwill do without reassurance.
烂角
Son of a bitch.
有空位了,一起玩吗?
Hey, looks like we got a coupla seats opening up. You wanna come join us?
你开玩笑的吧?
Are you serious?
红番扑克?你们怎么玩?
What, Injun poker? Hey, how do you boys do that again?
牌放在头上,白痴都一目了然
Card on the head, only fool can't see it is you.
到底要不要过来坐?
You want to come on over, or what?
算我一份
Cut me in.
我想玩大小通吃 最大最小都赢,A可以当两头
I'm thinkin' Fiery Cross, high-low, hoggers OK, ace plays both ways...
别被他唬住
Hey, don't let him scare you.
反正就是大小通吃 了不起浪费时间跟金钱
If you've ever played a high-low game, it's like any other. Waste of time and money.
出底钱,酋长
Well, ante up... Chief.
你怎么知道我是酋长?
How'd you know I was a chief?
你一定看过我戴着战帽洗澡
You must've seen me showering with my war bonnet.
-发牌 -我们可不收贝壳串
- Deal 'em up, deal 'em up. - You know, we don't take wampum here.
真好听
Beautiful.
听好了,各位
All right, then.
命令终于下来了
Orders finally came through.
我们明天早上出航
We ship out tomorrow morning.
目的地：塞班岛
Destination: the island of Saipan,
它是我们通往东京的跳板
which is one of the stepping stones we gotta take on our road show to Tokyo.
攻下这个岛极具战略价值
It's of strategic importance that we capture this island.
可以成立海军前进基地
We can get ourselves an advanced naval base
和空军跑道 以便B29降落和加油
and an airstrip to land and refuel B-29's
那么东京就在轰炸航程内了
and get our bombers within range of Tokyo.
目前塞班岛是日本的领土 上面驻守有三万日军
Now, Saipan is Japanese soil, and there's 30,000 of 'em dug in.
他们必然会死守到底
They're gonna fight for every square inch,
因为那是他们的家 但我们要把它抢过来!
because it's their home, but we're gonna take it away from 'em!
杀日本鬼子!
Yeah! Kill me some Japs!
我们是整个师的先头部队
We're gonna be in front of the whole damn division.
我们是全师的耳目
We're gonna be the eyes and the ears.
我们要闻出敌军的所在地点
We're gonna be sniffin' out enemy positions,
协调海军炮火
coordinating the naval gunfire -
任务跟四个月来的训练一样 没问题吧?
exactly what we've been training to do for the last four months. All right?
司令部派来了几位通信兵
Now, we got some new radiomen from headquarters.
二等兵白马
There's a Private Whitehorse...
和亚吉
and Yahzee...
以及两位中士 恩得斯和韩德森
and a couple of sergeants, Enders and Henderson,
他们…依据命令…
who, if I'm understanding these orders correctly,
将掩护我们的纳瓦荷战士
will be covering our Navajos' asses.
你他妈的,乔伊恩得斯!
Goddamn you, Joe Enders!
现在轮到我们赴汤蹈火了
..but I'm tellin' you, we'll be steppin' into our share of the shit nonetheless.
有问题吗?
Any questions?
听起来你好像快挂了
Sounds like you're dying.
这可以帮你消除气味
These might help get rid of the taste.
查理和我从圣地牙哥坐船来时 也吐得死去活来
Charlie and I, we both lost it on the boat ride from San Diego.
亚历桑那有水的地方并不多
Not many bodies of water in Arizona.
口气清香糖还蛮有用的
Life Savers really helped.
要不要来一个?
You want a Life Saver?
你为什么来这里?
What are you doin' here?
想帮个小忙罢了
Just trying to help.
我不是这个意思
Not what I meant.
你是说,我为什么从军?
You mean what am I doing in this uniform?
战争也跟我有关啊,中士
It's my war too, Sergeant.
为我的国家、土地、同胞而战
I'm fighting for my country, for my land, for my people.
我担心的倒不是你的同胞
Not your people I'm worried about.
恩得斯,我是个密码战士
Listen, Enders, I'm a codetalker.
我只要二分半钟就可以解读 一般人一小时才懂的东西
It takes me two-and-a-half minutes to do what used to take an hour.
有位官阶比你高很多的人
Now, somebody wearing a lot more stripes than you
认为这东西很有价值
thinks that's worth something.
子弹飞到头上时 记得叫我帮你计时
Remind me to time you when you got bullets flying over your head.
你到底是哪里不高兴?
What the hell's wrong with you?
Shave his belly with a rusty razor
Shave his belly with a rusty razor Early in the morning!
从蒙特祖玛圣殿
From the halls of Montezuma
到屈波里海岸
To the shores of Tripoli
我们为祖国而战
We will fight our country's battles
从陆地打到海上
On the land and on the sea
主要为权利和自由而战
First to fight for right and freedom
也为保卫我们的荣誉
And to keep our honor clean
我们为自己感到骄傲
We are proud to claim the title
我们是美国海军陆战队
Of United States Marines
嗨
Hi.
耳朵怎么样?
How's that ear?
不管怎样,痛时记得吃两颗药
Not that you'd ever admit it, but if it starts aching, take a couple of those.
第二天早上再打电话给我
And call me in the morning.
明早你就不在这了吧?
You're not gonna be here in the morning, are you?
要走了也不请我喝一杯
Shipping out without even buying me a drink.
骚扰军人,你害不害羞?
Ought to be ashamed of yourself, hustling a... hustling marines.
你爱喝什么?
What's your poison?
哟,我可能会热情奔放哦 随便都好
Jeez, might as well go all out. I'll get a shot of something.
兰姆吧
Rum.
艾迪,来杯巴卡迪
Eddie, give me a shot of Bacardi.
两杯
Make that two.
陪我一起喝嘛
May as well join me, huh?
好啊
- Why not? - OK.
谢谢
Thank you.
敬这场战争
Well... to war.
“1944年6月16日本塞班岛”
THE JAPANESE ISLAND OF SAIPAN JUNE 16, 1944
快,快,快!
Let's go, let's go, let's go!
叫他们散开!
Get those men spread out!
查理,快!
Charlie, come on, come on, come on!
跟上!
Come on, keep up!
继续走!加油!
Let's go, let's go, let's go! Come on!
-我怎么样? -非常优秀
- How am I doin'? - You're good.
继续前进!
Let's go!
跟紧一点
Stay on my ass.
我叫你跟紧一点!
I told you to stay on my ass!
-蹲低一点! -出来!
- Stay low! - Get out of there!
冲!
Go!
救他出来!
Get him outta there!
Get me outta here!
-不要动,可恶! -救他出来!
- Hold still, damn it! - Get him outta there!
你们这些王八蛋!
You sons of bitches!
佛第诺,掩护我!
Fortino! Cover me!
白马,趴下!
Whitehorse, get down!
趴下!
Get down!
帕帕斯!
Pappas!
救护兵!
Corpsman!
钢盔是戴在头上的! 救护兵!
Helmet goes on your head! Corpsman!
看看他的状况
Take care of him.
手压住这里!
Put a hand on this.
坦克!坦克!
Tank! Tank! Tank!
准备好了吗?丢!
You ready? Go! Go!
哈利根,烧它个鸡飞狗跳!
Harrigan, light it up!
前进,继续加油
Let's go, boys! Keep up the fight!
你有中弹吗?
Are you hit? Are you hit?
你没事,你很好
You're OK. You're good, you're good.
-你还好吧,奇克? -还能杀人,枪头
- Are you OK, Chick? - Still in the hunt, Gunny.
-哈利? -想干掉我没那么容易!
- Harri? - You ain't gettin' rid of me that easy.
-趴低一点! -奈里!帕帕斯!
- Stay low! - Nellie? Pappas?
我们很好
Yeah, we're good.
希腊人有过度换气征兆
Greek's predisposed to hyperventilate.
什么?
What?
一兴奋我就喘不过气来
I can't breathe when I get excited.
干!那你女朋友可累了!
Goddamn! Must be hell on your gal!
恩得斯,通知海军 轰掉他们的炮阵地
Enders, get the navy on the horn and tell 'em to dig out those guns.
目标座标,D1
Target reference... dog one...
右700米
right 700.
海拔050
Elevation zero-five-zero.
把座标传出去!
Relay the damn coordinates!
亚历桑那!亚历桑那!
Arizona! Arizona!
“美国海军加利佛尼亚号”
USS CALIFORNIA
好像水底传来的，是英语吗？
It sounds like they're underwater. Is it English?
目标座标,D1
Target reference, dog one,
南700米,海拔050
south 700, elevation zero-five-zero.
右200米!
Right 200!
高50!立刻开火!
Up 50. Fire for effect.
前进!
Let's go!
走!
Move!
哈利根!
Harrigan!
火攻碉堡!
Torch the box!
干掉他!
Kill him!
王八蛋!
Goddamn it!
干
Shit.
奈里,炸药包带着!
Nellie. Take the satchel charge.
听到了没?快!
You hear me? Move!
你会掩护我吧?
You're gonna cover me, right?
我一起去,从左翼进攻
I'll go with you. We flank left.
我掩护你们,烟幕弹
I'll cover you. Smoke and cover.
我办得到
I can do this.
投掷烟幕弹!
Smoke 'em up!
掩护他!
Cover up.
操!
Shit!
操,日本队被达阵了!
Shit. Goddamn Nipponese touchdown!
“塞班岛”
0500时提高警觉
Heads up around 0500.
补给品和弹药会送过去，完毕
You're going to have replacements and ammo coming up. Over.
收到，请确认新口令
Roger. Make sure they have the new password.
问“猎风”，答“战士”
Challenge: "Wind." Answer: "Talkers."
一位纳瓦荷弟兄取的名字
That's what one of our Navajo brothers calls us.
觉得怎么样？完毕
What do you think? Over.
“猎风战士”我喜欢
"Windtalkers," I like it.
好拉，老友，一夜平安，完毕
OK, Kemo Sabe, keep your butts down tonight. Over.
这口粮真难吃
Biscuits? How can you ruin biscuits?
你还真他妈爱抱怨
You are a whiny son of a bitch right now, aren't you?
塞班晚上10点,东岸几点?
2200 hours in jungle hell - what does that make it on the East Coast?
我怎么会知道
How the fucking hell should I know?
7点…
Just seven...
星期日早上8点
It's 8am, Sunday morning.
希望我的床昨晚没被篡位
I hope my side of the bed didn't get taken up Saturday night.
这么不放心她,迟早胃溃疡
Nell, you'll give yourself an ulcer, you keep worrying about her.
这样我就可以回罗德岛了
Might get my ass sent back to Rhody, though.
罗德岛辣妹不少哦
There's plenty of dollies outside of Rhode Island, Nell. Many plenty.
-这里肯定没半个 -这还用说
- Well, there sure as shit ain't any here. - Ain't that the truth.
她们全挤在德通海滩 世界上最美的女人
That's cos they're all in Daytona Beach. The most beautiful women in the world.
战前有一次
This one time, before the war,
我躺在沙滩上,有个美女… 叫茉莉,从水里上岸来
I'm lyin' on the beach and this sweet little thing named Molly comes out the water.
走到我身边,问我饿不饿
She walks straight up to me and asks me if I'm hungry...
因为她只吃条小热狗
cos she's havin' a weenie roast.
哇靠!
Shit! Damn.
于是我和茉莉…爽
Yeah, me and Molly, oh boy.
现在却困在塞班岛上 身上背个巨无霸打火机
Now I'm on Saipan with this giant Zippo strapped to my back
专门烤人肉
and I'm roastin' human beings.
为什么会自愿从军 我实在搞不懂
Why I volunteered... beyond me.
我倒是觉得蛮骄傲的
Damn, I'm proud to be here.
我全家都是海军陆战队
My whole family's been in the Corps.
老爸是终身职
My old man, he's a lifer.
海上陆上都不可一世
An ass-kicker on the land and on the sea.
在家一样作威作福
Around the house too.
现在可能收敛点了
Maybe now he'll back off.
帕帕斯
Pappas, I...
希望你能帮个忙
I want you to do me a favor.
万一我出了事
If anything should happen to me,
这个请交给我太太
you make sure that my wife gets this.
这是她亲手挑的
I mean, she picked them out and all.
不要说这种话,奈尔
Don't talk like that, Nell.
连玩笑都不要开
You don't even joke about shit like that.
戴回去,你会平安回家
Now you put that ring back on. You're goin' home.
喝过才谢我还不迟
Don't thank me till you've tried it.
发信时你不在
You missed mailcall.
“乔伊恩得斯收 丽塔史维登寄”
他们在干嘛?
What the hell are they doin'?
不知道,日落后就忙个不停
I don't know. They've been doin' it since sundown.
听起来像是祈祷
Sounds like some kind of prayer.
或许他们知道我们的命令
Maybe they know our orders.
你下得了手吗,乔伊?
Think you could do it, Joe?
不要一直想这问题,韩德森
Give it a rest, Henderson.
不要想?我试过,可是…
Give it a rest? I keep tryin', but...
该杀的是日本人,不是自己人
I'm here to kill Japs, not marines.
你是个勇士，亚吉
I saw you a warrior, Yahzee...
你是家族的荣耀
You will make your family proud.
你在干嘛,老弟?
What the hell you think you're doin', boy?
正要穿上制服
Getting on my uniform.
知道你跟日本人 有什么差别吗?
You know the difference between you and a Jap, Yahzee?
差在制服
It's that uniform.
仅此而已
That's it.
我了解你们这些人
See, I know you people.
我清楚你们这些凤眼野蛮人
I know what kind of slanty-eyed savage you are, boy.
落单时当心一点
You ought to be careful out here all alone.
没有人照顾你时
No baby-sitter.
我可能会把你看成日本鬼子
I might just take you for a Jap.
你要让我穿衣服吗,奇克?
You gonna let me get dressed, Chick?
还是继续演无知的白痴?
Or keep demonstrating what an ignorant fool you are?
无知的白痴是吧?
How's that for an ignorant fool?
拿啊,你试试看
Go ahead, try again.
你不是想干什么吗?
You gonna do somethin'?
奇克,住手
Chick! Come on!
走开!
Get off me!
-你没事吧,班? -没事
- You OK, Ben? - Yeah.
班?恶心
Ben? Shit.
我以为他是日本人 杀我弟兄,偷穿制服
I thought he was a Jap. You know, killed some marine for that uniform.
再扯嘛,奇克
Sure you did, Chick.
死红番不像日本鬼子吗?
Damn Injun looks just like a Jap, don't he?
我不是死红番
Look, I'm no damn Injun.
我是纳瓦荷人 母系是苦水族,父系是塔楼族
I'm Navajo, of the Bitter Water People, born for the Towering House clan.
但长相蛮像日本人
But you do look like a Nip.
下次要洗澡先通知我 否则我踢你屁股
Next time you decide to take a bath, Private, let me know, or I'll kick your ass.
妈的败类
Fuckin' shitbird.
他随时都需要人照顾
Supposed to be with a baby-sitter all the time, I thought.
连出去打鱼时也一样
Out here huntin' salmon and shit.
昨晚你看到的是 我们的庇护仪式
That ceremony you saw last night? It's called a protection ceremony.
纳瓦荷人相信尸体未安葬前 灵魂会一直待在附近
Navajo believe, untila body's given a proper burial, the spirits stay near it.
我们称恶灵为仙邸司
Chindis - that's what we call evilspirits. Demons.
我从小不曾认真想过这问题
I haven't thought much about it since I was a kid.
直到我目睹这些死尸
Till I saw those dead bodies.
你是说你看得到鬼魂?
You telling me you saw ghosts, Private?
不,我是说我不再害怕了
No, Sergeant. I'm telling you I won't freeze up again.
因为你朋友在你额头上抹灰?
Because your buddy smeared ash on your forehead?
没错,因为我朋友 在我额头上抹灰
That's right. Cos my buddy smeared ash on my forehead.
你看过鬼吗?
You ever see ghosts?
不要再问傻问题了 这是命令
No more stupid questions today, Private. That's an order.
真好听
Sounds beautiful.
无师自通吗?
You, uh, you self-taught?
我爸爸常吹
My dad was always playing.
他们不是说“拼不过他就…”
You know what they say: if you can't beat 'em...
正确,这是我爸送我的
No shit. My dad, he... he gave me this thing.
他以前叫我小猪魔笛
Used to call me the Pied Piper of the Pigs.
我一吹它们就过来吃饲料
Used to bring 'em in for feeding with this little tune I played.
我知道你不会停止吹笛子
I know I ain't gonna get you to quit playin' that thing, so...
所以“拼不过他就…”
like you just said, if you can't beat 'em...
我觉得声音不协调
I don't think it's gonna work.
反正别无他法,管他的
Well, we ain't got much else to do out here. What the hell?
好吧
OK.
你起音,我来和
All right, you lead off. I'll follow you.
第二侦查队0600出发
2nd Recon Company will move out at 0600
沿四号路搜索下去
and scout along road 04.
椰林西北边可能遭到轻微抵抗
You can expect light resistance northwest of the palm grove. Over.
收到，何谓“轻微”？ 没有任何抵抗是轻微的，完毕
Roger. What do you mean, light? No resistance is light! Over.
记住座右铭不问为什么
Remember, marine, "Ours is not to question why,
只管拼命与牺牲
ours is but to do or die."
“永远忠诚”完毕
Semper Fi. Over.
亲爱的乔伊,你到底怎么了?
Dear Joe, how the hell are you?
因为你不爱写信 就应该音讯全无吗?
Or, given that you're not much of a writer, should I not expect an answer?
报上说,我军战果辉煌
The newspapers say our boys are doing great.
但我想记者都没看到 肯尼欧湾医院的伤兵
But I don't think the reporters have been to Kaneohe Bay Hospital.
前几天在瓦基基捡到只流浪狗
I found a stray dog the other day on Waikiki.
带回家洗个澡留下来养
I gave him a bath and took him in.
它令我想起你,但它比较可爱
He reminded me of you - but cuter.
至少它晚上给我温暖
At least he keeps me warm at night.
我尽量不想你 也不去想可能发生的事
I try not to think about you. About what might be happening over there.
但是,有时候躺在床上
But sometimes, when I'm lying in bed,
忍不住担心你的处境
I can't keep myself from wondering where you are.
和过得好不好
How you're doing.
你在干嘛?
What the hell you doin'?
写信给我儿子
Writing a letter to my son.
你忘了命令?不准流出一个字
Forget your orders? No letters out.
上面不准邮件进入保育区
Command don't want postmarks going to the reservation.
没听到吗?
Hey! You hear me?
我回家后他就看得到啦
I thought that he might read 'em when I get home.
他叫什么名字?
What's his name?
你儿子
Your son.
乔治,乔治华盛顿
It's George. George Washington.
乔治华盛顿亚吉
George Washington Yahzee.
听起来蛮响亮的
It's got a bit of a ring to it.
我太太不太喜欢
My wife wasn't so sure.
她比较传统
She's a little more traditional.
-好漂亮的一家人 -给我看看,亚吉
- Nice-looking family. - Let's see, Yahz.
乔治很有个性 他有自己的想法
Yeah, that George, he's quite a character. He's got a mind of his own.
我可以抽一根吗?
Can I try one of those?
-你抽烟? -抽着玩的
- You smoke? - Not really.
-下来! -快下车!
- Dismount! - Get out of the truck!
动作快!
Let's go! Let's go!
-跟我来! -走!
- Follow me! - Let's go!
我中弹了!
- I'm hit! - Yahzee!
亚吉
Yahzee!
我中弹了!
I'm hit!
拿下来!好烫!
Take it off! It burns!
你没中弹,闭嘴!
You're not hit. Just shut up. You're not hit.
-散开! -动作快!
- Spread out! - Move!
-炸弹从哪来的? -我们自己人
- Where the hell are they comin' from? - From us.
-什么? -那不是日本人的炮
- What? - They're not Jap guns.
-自己人炸自己人? -我们应该走四号路
- We're getting shot at by our own guys? - We're supposed to be on road 04.
-通知团部 -没办法!
- Get the regiment on the horn. - I can't!
-告诉他们炸到自己人 -不行!无线电炸坏了
- Tell 'em they're shelling... - I can't! The radio's out. It's been hit.
-他们炸太近了 -日本鬼子一定在我们前面
- They're firing too short! - The Japs gotta be way ahead of us.
想点办法
Do somethin'.
跟我来
Shit... Follow me!
-我们走错路了 -干!
- We're on the wrong fuckin' road! - Goddamn it!
完蛋了!
God.
龟孙子
Son of a bitch!
不要怕,老哥!
I got you, mac!
救护兵!
Corpsman!
奈里!
Nellie!
救护兵!
Corpsman!
你说的没错,乔伊
You were right, Joe.
我长得像日本人
I do look like a Nip.
你在说什么?
What the hell are you talking about?
穿上他们的制服
Putting on that Jap uniform.
用他们的无线电 通知我方停火
Trying to get one of their radios, call off our guns.
-笨主意 -闭嘴,让他说完
- That's stupid. - Shut up. Let him talk.
-他不能出去 -这里不由你指挥,恩得斯
- He's not goin' out there. - You're not in charge here, Enders.
我身负命令,枪头 我要保护他
I got orders, Gunny. He's my responsibility!
他还年轻啊! 你们在杀自己人!
He's just a kid! You killed your own!
你们有毛病啊! 你们在杀自己人!王八蛋!
What's wrong with you? You killed your own! Sons of bitches!
你们在杀自己人!
You killed your own!
-你确定要这么做? -马上就知道答案了,长官
- Sure you're up to this? - Find out soon enough, sir.
-你想干嘛? -我跟他去
- What the hell are you doin' there? - I'm goin' with him.
如果你没意见的话
If that's OK with you.
枪给我
Give me the rifle.
Horyo-da.
“战俘”的日本话
It's Jap for prisoner.
Horyo-da.
好啦,大家准备
All right, everybody be ready.
Horyo-da!
冲啊!
Now!
打我
Hit me. Hit me.
不要打我!
Please don't hit me!
亚吉
Yahzee!
杀了他!
Kill him!
快点,杀了他!
Goddamn it, kill him!
去无线电那!
Get on the radio!
白鲍威,这是红卡森!
Bowie White, Bowie White, this is Carson Red!
停火!你们在炸自己人!
Cease fire! Cease fire! You're shelling marines!
中士!
Sergeant!
停火!
Cease fire! Cease fire!
距离加325米,立刻射击!
Add 325, fire for effect!
调整!加325米,立刻射击!
Redirect fire. Add 325, fire for effect.
走啦!
Let's go!
摇高点!快!
Crank it up! Let's go!
开火!
Commence fire!
Fire!
奏效了
Well, I'll be.
请问什么事,上校?
Colonel. Can I help you, sir?
我想找一位恩得斯中士 约瑟夫恩得斯
I'm looking for Sergeant Enders. Joseph F Enders.
恩得斯
Enders.
是的,长官
Yes, sir.
据报你非常神勇
Report I read claims you went above and beyond.
长官
Sir?
我们已推荐你接受表扬
You've been recommended for commendation.
我非常同意,但何必等待…
And I concur. But I don't see any point in you having to wait around
繁复的公文往返
for all those formalities to work themselves out.
我手边正好有个勋章
Not when I got one of these handy.
恭喜,恩得斯
Congratulations, Enders.
你救了不少同胞
You saved a lot of marines.
这不是我一个人的功劳,长官 多亏了二等兵班亚吉的帮忙
I wasn't alone in that, sir. I couldn't have done it without Private Ben Yahzee.
对,那位印地安人
Oh... Right. The, uh, Indian.
抱歉,他是纳瓦荷人 母系苦水族
Begging the colonel's pardon, he's a Navajo, of the Bitter Water People,
父系塔楼族
born for the Towering House clan.
当然,纳瓦荷人,塔楼族
Of course. Navajo. Towering House clan.
继续保持下去,恩得斯
You keep up the good work, Enders.
把这个寄给奈里的太太
Send that to Nellie's wife.
每次都有你的信,恩得斯
You ever not miss mailcall, Enders?
我妈说,人家花时间写信
My mom says somebody takes the time to write a letter,
你该花时间好好读
you should read the letter.
你妈肯让你喝酒吗?
Does she let you drink, your mother?
不肯,但她又不在这
No. But she's not here.
-这是什么酒? -确定不是法国红酒
- What is it? - Well, it ain't Chianti, I'll tell you that.
米酒类,是日本清酒 反正会醉就是了
It's rice wine. It's Jap sake. But it does the trick.
你有多少这种东西?
How much of this crap do you have anyway?
你这只耳朵有问题对不对?
You have a little trouble with that ear, don't you, Joe?
问题在内耳,耳鼓耳膜之类的
Ah, real problem's the inner ear. It's anvils and stirrups and shit.
我的平衡感不太好
I'm a little out of balance.
你在山丘上表现很好,亚吉
You done good on that hill today, Yahzee.
是啊,表现不错吧?
Yeah, I did, didn't I?
一定了你一跳
I bet I surprised the shit out of you.
你的情操很崇高,乔伊
It was a noble thing that you did, Joe.
把银星勋章给奈里的太太
To give your Silver Star to Nellie's wife.
我才不在乎奖章
I don't give a shit about medals.
他们给我的第一枚
The first one they gave me...
被我扔到海里去
I threw it into the ocean.
那次是为了什么事?
What'd you get that one for?
因为我撑着没死
For not dyin'.
15个战友一起接受表扬 他们悉数阵亡
The 15 men who fought with me got decorated too. For dying.
所以…
So...
中尉前一晚就战死了
Lieutenant was killed the night before and...
士官们也全死在登陆艇里
none of the sergeants even made it out of the landing craft, so...
所以只好由我指挥 我第一次发号施令
that left me in charge. It was my first command.
上面下令死守 某个鸟不拉屎的沼泽
Orders were to hold some shitty swamp marsh on the ass-end of nowhere.
我只好听命行事
And I did.
我手下的弟兄
All of the men under my command...
信任我的人
men who trusted me...
全都求我撤退
who begged me to pull back...
结果没有一个生还
not one of them made it.
除了一个固执的浑球
Just one stupid asshole.
他们因此给我银星勋章
And for that, they gave me the Silver Star.
他们叫什么名字?
What were their names?
说他们的故事
It might be good to tell a story about 'em.
最好也知道他们的名字和长相
You know, who they were and what they were like.
纳瓦荷人鸟规矩真多 要干什么?
What a magical pile of Navajo horseshit. What the hell for?
向他们致敬
To honor them.
纪念他们
Their memory.
那不是你的错,乔伊 你是听命行事
You know, it wasn't your fault, Joe. You were just followin' orders.
是啊
Yeah.
我是他妈的杰出陆战队
I'm a good fuckin' marine.
所以派这个任务给我
That's why they gave me this detail.
是喔
Yeah.
我是他妈的杰出陆战队
I'm a good fuckin' marine.
乔伊  怎么
- Joe! - What?
你他妈的,乔伊恩得斯
Goddamn you, Joe Enders!
没错
Really.
不要想太多
It's all right.
来,乔伊,我扶你
Come on, Joe. I got you.
干什么?
What the fuck?
我没醉死,亚吉,别乱整
I ain't that drunk, Yahzee. You cut that horseshit out.
“塔那帕村第二侦查队”
什么时候抵达村庄？
What's your expected arrival to the village? Over.
大约1500，空军侦查报告
Around 1500. Aerial Reconnaissance reports
没有活动，好像蛮安全的
no movement, looks secure.
要求热食与信件，完毕
Request hot chow and mailif possible. Over.
混合草莓与这瑞典玩意儿 就成了优酪乳
I'm gonna mix my daddy's strawberries in this Swedish concoction called yoghurt.
所幸美国人会自创口味
God willin', America will develop the taste.
战后你想干嘛,查理?
What about you, Charlie? What's life got in store for you after this mess?
奇克拿来当女朋友的绵羊?
Sheep? As in Chick's girlfriend, sheep?
查理家的羊群是四州最多的
Charlie's family owns the biggest flock in the Four Corners area.
不是盖的?
No shit?
-你是富翁嘛,白马 -还好啦
- You a rich man, Whitehorse? - We do OK.
我要成立计程车队 那是我致富的秘诀
Taxis. A whole stinkin' fleet of 'em. That's how I'm making my millions.
然后我要回到我的故乡
And then I'm goin' back to the motherland.
在圣多里尼峭壁盖栋别墅
I'm gonna build myself a villa on the cliffs of Santorini.
圣多里尼,哇,奢华
Ah, Santorini, my friends - that's living.
不错,你呢,吉?
Sounds nice. What about you, Zee?
我考虑去教书
Thinkin' about teaching.
引进新知识到保育区
Ah, teaching. Bring a little something back to the reservation?
事实上,是将保育区的知识 介绍给全世界
Actually, more interested in bringing some of the reservation back to the world.
希望能到大学教美国历史
Hoping to teach college. American history.
很符合我们的需要
Oh, that's just what we need.
亚吉告诉大学生 卡司特怎么在小彼弘被剥头皮
Yahzee teachin' college boys about Custer's scalpin' at Little Bighorn.
奇特卡森逼纳瓦荷人 迁徙三千哩又怎么说?
And what about Kit Carson, and what they did to the Navajo in the Long Walk?
没读过吧,奇克?
You ever read about that, Chick?
一定没有
Didn't think so.
你呢,乔伊?
How about you, Joe?
-什么? -战后你想干嘛?
- What? - What are you doin' after this mess?
战争总是会结束的
It's gotta end sometime.
亲爱的乔伊,今天有个好消息
Dear Joe, we got great news today.
罗斯福总统宣布取消 夏威夷的灯火管制
President Roosevelt announced the end of blackouts on Hawaii.
本以为遥遥无期
We thought the day would never come.
10点仍有宵禁但影响不到我
There's still a ten o'clock curfew, but it doesn't matter to me.
值班12小时后 累得只有精力写信
After a 12-hour shift I'm too tired to do anything but write letters.
真正感觉到战况不错 战争随时都有可能结束了
There is a real sense that the war is going well, and could be over soon.
越来越想你 你到底是死是活呢?
I think about you more and more. If you're alive or dead out there.
我每天查信 心想迟早会有答案
I check the mailevery day, knowing there's going to be an answer.
你有收到我的信吗,乔伊?
Are you reading these, Joe?
听到我的话吗?
Are you listening?
-左翼没有危险 -这区没有危险
- We're secure on the left side. - Area's secured.
做好防御工事
Set up defense positions.
奇克,负责扎营
Chick, bed 'em down for the night.
哈利
Harri.
怎么回事？
What's wrong?
好痛
I'm hurting.
这里有些止痛药
Here's some pain reliever.
别担心，你没事
Don't worry, you'll be fine.
谢谢，大叔
Thank you, Uncle.
听起来蛮有感觉的
That's startin' to sound like something.
不晓得你是个艺术家
I didn't know you were an artist.
随便涂鸦
Oh, it's stupid.
小时候常在祖母厨房桌上画
It's just something I would do as a kid on my grandmother's kitchen table.
很不错
Well, it's nice.
你信天主教?
You Catholic?
以前啦
I used to be.
正好想起受坚信礼的事
I was thinkin' about when they confirmed me.
八岁那年,他们帮我抹圣水
I was eight, and they anointed me with the holy water.
我还记得
And I remember...
他们说我是基督的战士
they told me I was a soldier of Christ.
不晓得什么时候迷失了自己
I guess somewhere along the way I must have switched units.
是油
It's oil.
坚信礼不用水,是用油
They don't use holy water to confirm. They use oil.
我家也信天主教
I was raised Catholic too.
上保育区内的教会学校
Mission school on the reservation.
神父作弥撒时 不喜欢我们说纳瓦荷语
It's funny. Fathers didn't like us talking Navajo at Mass.
有个礼拜天我忘记了
Of course, one Sunday I forgot.
被处罚绑在地下室的暖炉上
They punished me by tying me to the radiator in the basement.
整整两天
For two days.
记得我当时也是八岁
I think I was eight too.
现在可以自由说纳瓦荷语了
Well, they're sure lettin' you talk Navajo now. Yeah.
战争结束后 或许你该来看看纳瓦荷村
You know, when this is over, maybe you should come out to Navajo country.
纪念碑河谷很美,很幽静
Monument Valley is a beautiful place. It's peaceful.
可以尝试军队里没有的东西
You know, we could do some things that you don't do in the Corps.
比如骑马,吃炸面包,打猎
Like ride horses, eat fry bread, do some hunting...
骑马
Horses.
再说啦 到亚历桑那有好长一段路
I don't know. It's a pretty long drive to Arizona.
很值得,你可以看看我儿子
But it might be worth it. You know, you could meet my son.
他也可以见见乔伊恩得斯
And he could meet Joe Enders,
保护他瘦弱老爸的恩人
the guy who watched over Daddy's scrawny ass.
你一定是个好父亲,班
You must be a very good father, Ben.
班?你以前不曾这样叫我
Ben. You know, you've never called me that before.
恩得斯是哪一国名字?
Enders. What kind of name is that anyway?
意大利,原本叫恩卓菲尼 被艾利斯岛移民局简化了
It's Italian. Used to be Endrolfini before some asshole at Ellis Island got hold of it.
上尉要发一封密码信到司令部
Captain needs to code a message back to command post.
你就是那个印地安人?
You the Indian?
是的,我是那个印地安人
Yeah, I'm the Indian.
只要几分钟,马上送你回来
It's just a few minutes' drive. We'll get you back in no time.
-我有话跟你说,枪头 -等我一下
- I need to speak with you, Gunny. - Yeah. Give me a second.
今天寄来的,吃过腌鲱鱼吗?
Got this with the mailtoday. You ever had pickled herring?
我想调职
I need out.
你在说什么?
What the hell are you talkin' about?
目前的职务
This detail.
我的任务
My duty.
我无法执行
I can't do it.
我需要你,恩得斯
Well, I need you, Enders.
你救过很多同胞的命
Yeah. You've been saving a lot of marines.
我要向营部司令申诉 我要调职
I'm requesting mast with battalion commander. I want out.
是吗?大家都是妈妈的儿子 谁不想调职
Oh, yeah? You and me and every other mother's son. We all want out.
只要东条英机和希特勒不死
Well, as long as there's a Tojo and a Hitler out there
我们就得继续战,懂吗?
we have to keep on fighting. Is that understood?
-你误会了 -我听得一清二楚
- You're not hearing me. - I'm hearing you just fine.
现在全世界都在打仗
Now, there's a war goin' on worldwide,
没空理会你的需求和愿望
and it ain't bein' waged on your wants and wishes.
好好去睡一觉,这是命令
Now you get some sack time. That's an order.
去你的!我下不了手!
Goddamn it! I can't do it!
我无法执行任务!
I can't perform my duty!
嘿,小朋友
Hey there, sweetheart.
嗨,没有关系
Hi. It's OK.
不要哭,不会有事
You don't have to cry. You're gonna be all right.
我送你一个礼物
Got a present for you.
巧克力
This is chocolate.
吃吃看,很好吃
You see, you eat it... and it's good.
很好吃
It's good.
要不要尝尝看?
You want some?
下次记得先嚼一嚼
You'll have to chew it next time. Here.
哈利根,走!
Harrigan, go!
炸弹过来了!
Incoming!
跑!
Run!
走!快跑!
Go! Run!
哈利根!叫她跑!
Harrigan! Make her run!
快点!来这边!
Come on! To me!
哈利根!
Harrigan!
该走了!
Come on, keep moving!
退回来!
Fall back!
求救!求救!
Help! Help!
不能让他们活捉我们
I can't let 'em take us.
说什么呀?
What are you talking about?
留他活口
Don't kill him.
他很重要
He's important.
我们需要拷问他
We need to interrogate him.
恩得斯
Enders!
我找不到公牛和白马
I can't find Ox or Whitehorse.
你有看到他们吗?
Have you seen them?
他在那里
He's over there.
噢,天啊
Oh, shit...
这里不是应该很安全吗? 怎么回事?
This was supposed to be a secured area! What happened?
我杀了他
I killed him.
你什么?
You... you what?
我用手榴弹 丢过去把他炸个粉碎
I took my grenade and... and I threw it and I blew him up.
你他妈的疯了!
What the hell is wrong with you?
亚吉
Yahzee!
亚吉,不要!
Yahzee! Yahzee, no!
起来!
Get up!
来呀,动手啊
Come on. You can do it.
放过他
- Yahzee. - Let him go.
亚吉,不要
Yahzee, no.
为何不…动手啊!
Go on. Why can't... Come on. Do it.
-动手啊! -不
- Do it! - No.
我们听说白马的事了，亚吉 我们会表扬他的功绩
We heard about Whitehorse, Yahzee. We shall honor his name and his memory.
再会，查理再会
Farewell, Charlie, farewell.
是的，查理再会
Yes, Charlie, farewell.
你知道,白马…救过我一命
You know, Whitehorse... he saved my bacon.
不知道乔治卡斯特会怎么想
Wonder what George Armstrong Custer would make of that.
记得祖父以前坐在廊下 讲猎印地安人的事
I remember my granddaddy sittin' on the porch talkin' about huntin' Indians,
讲得简直像猎地鼠一般
like he was talkin' about gophers or somethin'.
猎一个赚三块美金
About gettin' paid three dollars per Comanche ear.
我知道很难想像
I know. Gets you thinkin'.
再过50年,或许我们 跟日本人会变成朋友
Another 50 years, who knows, we could be sittin' down with the Nipponese.
喝着清酒,随意哈拉
Drinkin' their sake, shootin' the shit...
聊看看还可以打谁
lookin' for somebody else's ass to kick.
你想太多了
You think too much.
第一次有人这样称赞我
First time I ever been accused of that.
“海陆第八营第二侦察连 塞班岛”
告诉过你别一个人到处晃
Thought I told you not to go traipsing around on your own.
你知道,查理祝福过我儿子 出生时,以纳瓦荷传统方式
You know, Charlie blessed my son in the Navajo way the day he was born.
他曾怀疑老美会保护我们
He wondered about cowboys watching Indians' backs.
老是感觉不对劲
Something about it didn't seem right.
我觉得查理只是多心
I thought it was Charlie just being Charlie.
他其实一点都不想来打仗 是我说服他的
He didn't even want to come to this damn war. I talked him into it.
或许你错了
Maybe you made a mistake.
大家可能都错了
Maybe we all did.
我只是奉命行事,班
I was following orders, Ben.
我奉命保护密码
My orders were to protect the code.
如果你们其中一人被补 一旦密,密码就没用了
If one of you got caught, talked, the code would be useless.
我只是奉命行事,班
I was following orders, Ben.
当然是,乔伊 你是他妈的杰出军人
Course you were, Joe. You're a damn good fuckin' marine.
海盗要找你
The Viking wants to see you.
他说马上
He says right away.
跟大伙说明一下怎么回事
I want you to brief everybody, make clear what's happenin'.
我打头阵没问题,枪头
All right. Got no problem with point, Gunny.
Yeah.
第八营已经出发了 我们要迎头赶上,领先他们
The 8th is moving out already and we need to be ahead of 'em.
目标是那边那块巨石
The destination is that big piece of rock you see over there.
这个岛的最后防御据点
The last defensible ridge on this island.
攻下那山头 塞班几乎就是我们的了
Now, thinkin' is, we take the mount, Saipan is pretty much ours.
昨天轰炸机 把山头炸得差不多了
Yesterday, bombers beat the shit out of that rock.
上面很紧张,可能遭到顽抗
The brass is nervous. They expected more resistance over there.
要我们过去查看一下
Now they want us to go over and check it out.
他们要我们去哪里?
So where the hell they got us now?
翻上山头
Goin' up the mountain.
偷窥一下
Have ourselves a little peek.
要密码战士打头阵是有原因的
That codetalker is out front for a reason.
他正好派上用场
That's exactly where I need him to be.
假如你俩之间有嫌隙
If there's still a problem between the two of you,
最好现在立刻摆平
I would like to straighten that out, right here, right now.
-我没事的,枪头 -好极了
- No problem here, Gunny. - That's good.
但我还有一个问题
But there's still one here.
你只须做你该做的事
You just do what you're supposed to do, Sergeant.
不多也不少
Nothing more, nothing less.
恩得斯
Enders.
恩得斯,又一封你的信
You got another letter.
不要动!
Freeze!
要命!我们站在地雷区中央!
Jesus Christ! We're in the middle of a goddamn minefield!
奇克会带我们脱离的,是吧?
Chick's gonna get us out. Right, Chick?
当然
Sure I am.
跟着奇克排一纵队
One line after Chick.
帕帕斯
Pappas.
走呀,希腊人
Move, Greek.
我的蛋蛋会被炸个粉碎!
I'm gonna get my fuckin' balls blown off out here!
亚吉,站住!
Yahzee! Stop!
躲开!
Move out!
亚吉
Yahzee!
射得好,帕帕斯
Nice shootin', Pap.
第八营进来了,查看另一边
The 8th's movin' in. We'd better check out the other side.
了解,你还好吧?
Got it. You all right?
奇克负责左翼,恩得斯到右翼 我们会用榴弹炮掩护你们
Chick, take the left flank. Enders, go right. We'll cover you with a 30.
-就位 -好了吗?
- On it. - All right?
好,走吧!
OK, let's go!
出发!
Move!
贺玛斯德!
Hjelmstad!
-快帮他! -枪头!
- Help him up! - Gunny!
快
Come on. Come on.
-天啊 -乔伊!
- Christ. - Joe! Joe!
撕开衣服
Tear him open.
要来点吗啡吗?
You want morphine?
-要来点吗啡吗? -好
- You want morphine? - Yeah.
你不会有事的,长官
You'll be all right, sir.
可恶!亚吉,过来!
Goddamn it, Yahzee, get over here!
干!
Fuck!
奇克,看着他
Chick... Stay with him.
有我在
I got ya.
我叫你照顾枪头
I told you to stay with Gunny.
枪头挂了
Gunny's gone.
我们出不去了,对不对?
We're not gonna make it out of here, are we, Joe?
我快没弹药了,乔伊
I'm runnin' out of ammo here, Joe.
我不想死在这S坑里
I don't wanna die in this shithole.
你不会死的
You're not gonna die.
不会有人死的
Nobody else is gonna die.
我们会活着 我们会活着出去
We're gonna make it. We're gonna make it out of here.
第八营被困在空地 我们必须请求空中支援
8th's caught out in the open. We gotta call in the flyboys.
我去拿那个无线电,掩护我
I'm gonna get that radio. Cover me.
无线电被他拿走了,亚吉!
He got the radio, Yahzee!
掩护我,我去了!
Cover me! I'm going!
退回去!
Stay back!
王八蛋!
Fuckers!
救不回你朋友的
It won't bring your friends back.
你懂什么叫朋友?
What do you know about friends?
快呼叫空中支援
Get us some air support!
白鲍威,红卡森呼叫 亚历桑那
Bowie White, this is Carson Red, Arizona.
重复,红卡森呼叫,亚历桑那
I say again, Carson Red, Arizona.
指示座标!
Coordinates!
2-20,麦克,36
Two-twenty, Mike, three-six.
好,走吧
All right, let's go.
我们要杀出重围
We're gonna make it outta here.
可恶,乔伊
Damn it, Joe.
快点动手
Just get it over with.
闭嘴,班
Shut up, Ben.
动手,乔伊
Do it, Joe.
动手啊!
Do it!
不能再死人了,班
No one else is gonna die, Ben.
不会再有人送命了
No one else is dying.
乔伊,我们成功了
Joe, we did it.
老天…
God...
老天
God!
Oh, God... Oh, Joe...
我们今天救了不少海陆弟兄
We saved a lot of marines today.
是啊,班
Yeah, we did, Ben.
查理…
Charlie...
你知道我不想杀他的
You know I didn't want to.
对吧?
Right?
圣母玛丽亚
Hail... HailMary...
万福
full of grace...
our...
天主与你同在
our Lord is with thee...
圣母玛丽亚,上帝之母
Holy Mary, mother of God...
保佑我们
pray for us...
我干掉最后一个了,乔伊
I got the last of 'em, Joe.
他名叫乔伊恩得斯
His name was Joe Enders...
南费城人
from South Philadelphia.
他是个英勇的战士
He was a fierce warrior.
是优秀海军陆战队
A good marine.
如果你要说他的故事,乔治
If you ever tell a story about him, George...
就说他是我的朋友
say he was my friend.
“纳瓦荷密码是塞班胜利的关键 太平洋区主要战役也靠它”
The Navajo Code was vital in the victory at Saipan and every major battle in the Pacific.
“纳瓦荷密码是塞班胜利的关键 太平洋区主要战役也靠它 这套密码始终未被破解”
The Navajo Code was vital in the victory at Saipan and every major battle in the Pacific It was never broken.